[Music]
hey hey welcome to day four of camp as
always I'm here with my camper
McKinley want to say good morning McKinley
McKinley is going to help us do a demo
here in just a sec what we're gonna make
today is we're gonna make a little
remote-control car so it's good even if
it's simulation to learn about motors so
today's focus is going to be about
motors and we've got a little demo for
you Sissy you want to be the driver for
the demo so what we've got set up here
so we've got a little remote-control car
so we're going to be learning about
motors in simulation but we've got
motors connected to the bottom of this
board it's just something this kit can do
which is fun we're gonna be controlling
it with remote control so Sissy go
ahead and send an F for forwards great
and send B for backwards and then go
ahead and try an L for a left turn and
then an R for a right turn and then just
to be silly send like three B's or
something to make it go backwards three
times as much we'll see if we can catch
it before it falls off the table I
always recommend the students that they
use the floor whenever they're doing
things with wheels but we're just kind
of doing it on the table I've also got
my speed set to super duper slow just so
it doesn't fall off the table but
obviously hit it sis oh no you'll find that
when it comes to two kids and
remote-control cars there's always a
desire to make things crash alright
let's go ahead and get started back over
to your seat
we'll teach you how to how to make
motors go you gotta figure out how to
make this silly car stop
maybe I'll just upend it
yeah I suppose I can unplug it as well
thanks so much for help there sis
alright so let's go ahead and get
started today so this is the the
finished circuit that we're building so
we'll build it piece by piece it's looks like
I do need to kill power on this thing
alright so I'm gonna go ahead and head
over to my dashboard so that I can make
a new circuit so click on new circuit
and the first pieces that we're going to
add are things that we've used quite a
bit we're gonna add a breadboard and
we're gonna add an Arduino so there are
some cool starters that we can use but I
kind of like to just start from the
basic so I'm gonna single click on
breadboard I find that sometimes single
click works better and then single click
over here sometimes I try to drag it
over but I forget that Tinkercad works
better with just like you click it then
you just kind of wait for a second and
then you drop it over here and so what
we're gonna do is we're gonna add these
two components they're gonna be
principal things we're gonna do we're
also going to add some motors there's a
bunch of different motors even in
Tinkercad and certainly in the real
world the ones that I'm gonna add are
these hobby motors these are fun these
come from a company in China called
Daegu they are inexpensive you can buy
them on a number of different websites
I think I got mine from robot shop
once upon a time this kit came with a
couple right but they're really good for
making like cars and things like that so
those are some things that we're gonna
use
other pieces just kind of while we're
getting our big pieces together it's
always nice to when you deal with motors
to be able to control the speed to like
make it go a little faster or a little
slower and a good way to do that is with
a potentiometer so you can always change
speeds in code but it can sometimes be
nice to have a potentiometer on the
board so I'm going to add two
potentiometers one that kind of controls
the speed of the right motor and then
the other it controls the speed of the
left motor now in simulation you could
control the speed with a single
potentiometer and they both like
go faster or slower together in
simulation but in real hardware every
motor is different
especially at super slow speeds so you
really do need two potentiometers in a
real system so that you can like make
the right go a little faster or the left
go a little faster so that it drives in
a fairly straight line so those are good
things to add to our circuit so now
we've got our two motors we've got our
board we've got our Arduino we've got
our trimpots so we control speed the
thing we're missing is we're missing
electronics to drive the motor so in the
same way that like you know you drive a
car all you do is you just you press the
gas pedal which tells the car hey make
the big motor go you don't like get out
and push right like that's not how it
works with electronics motors take a
lot of power they take a lot of umph
right and the microcontroller is not
made to do that the microcontroller is
just made to push the gas pedal right
and so he needs something else to make
the motor go so that was a big long
speech to say something that we need is
a transistor now there's two there's a
couple different types of transistors
one of them is called a MOSFET m o s f e t
we're not going to use a MOSFET today
but I want to tell you about it real
quick it's a type of transistor
it stands for like
metal-oxide-semiconductor field-effect
transistor that might be right I
don't even know and that is a good type
of transistor they're very popular at
turning something either on or off so if
you wanted your car to go in just
forward right then a MOSFET would be
great because they can turn the motor on
or I could turn it off but what it
doesn't give you the ability to do is
reverse right and we want reverse we've
got a car there's also an engine or a
NPN transistor but I'm not going to get
into that either the other thing that's
good is called an H bridge so an H
bridge is a chip so it's a little chip
that you put on your board they come in
all different flavors and we are going
to use an H bridge so I'm gonna single
click on the H bridge rotate it a couple
times and the way these chips work is
you plunk them right down right into the
middle of your breadboard
and so this H bridge chip has a lot of
pins on it right so it's got a lot of
different things going on I'm just going
to kind of tell you how do we connect it
but I'm just going to tell you the short
summary one side of the H bridge
controls one motor the other side of the
H bridge controls the other motor that's
kind of like the big picture and I think
that we're ready to start doing some
wires oh actually one more piece one
more piece so motors take a lot of power
right sissy do you like motors they make
me feel like like RRR right and they
need a lot of power and power comes from
batteries so this won't affect the
simulation but I'm gonna do it anyway
I'm gonna put on an external battery so
this guy actually has external batteries
on the bottom so that he can have more
power than just what the computer
provides and typically what you do is
use four double-a batteries so I've
brought over a double-a battery and this
big power pack is gonna drive the motors
instead of just using my computer to do
it just to kind of organize my circuit
a little bit I'm gonna put it kind of
like up above my breadboard if you lay
your parts out just like mine it might
make it easier for you but obviously
where the parts are at doesn't really
matter I'm just trying to like keep
things that are on the left on the left
and things that are on the right on the
right and that way I'll kind of like
build my car since I just put this big
power supply up here let's go ahead and
connect it so the first thing I want to
do is I want to connect ground to ground
I like for my ground wires to be black
just to like make them easier to see
colors of wires don't matter but I like
for my grounds to be black and the way
that I did that is after I put the wire
I hit the one key which is a shortcut
key to select like black
likewise I'm going to connect my power
and power is red so I'm going to connect
that wire and then hit the two so that
connects my power and ground so my big
power is on this rail and then I'm also
going to put my little power on the
other rail so I'm gonna connect ground
from here to here and that one's gonna
be black
and then I'm gonna use the 5v to connect
little power over on the side now you
know we're just kind of learning about
electronics and we're like why do we
have two different power supplies well
this is you know big power which is like
six volts and more than six volts it can
provide like up to over an amp of
current and this is little power it's
five volts and it can only provide like
a hundred milliamps of current so big
power little power now regardless of how
many powers you have you still only want
one ground so do this for me click on
the ground on this side and what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna connect ground to
the bottom of my breadboard and so what
that says is you know I've got a big
power and I've got a little power so
that's great but there is only one
ground and this is true for all
electronics you only want one ground on
things now we're ready to start
connecting our chip so our chip here
wants to drive the motors with big power
and the pin that you need to connect on
this chip to big power is the lower left
corner and if you want sometimes I like
to bend it around that's completely
optional just see can kind of see that
it's going to big power and then little
power goes into the top right and the
way this chip is designed is that it
wants little power so that it can do its
internal functionalities correctly just
like a microcontroller needs power and
then it needs big power because it'll
use that with some transistors it has inside
to drive the motors with big power
another thing these chips need is they
need is a lot of ground connections and so
all the middle pins so two on the left
and two on the right all need to get
connected to ground now you're like that's
silly
why do I have to connect four
different pins to ground because really
a chip only really needs one ground but
it's because of there's a lot of power
things going on here and they
wanted a really good path to get the
ground and so that's why there's four of
them it also made the packaging work out
better back when they designed this chip
many decades ago all right so that's
kind of the gist of it the next thing we
need to do is we need to connect our
motors to this thing so let's go ahead
and connect the left motor to the left
side and the right motor to the right
side so here's what I'm gonna do I'm
gonna take a pin just above ground and
I'm gonna connect it down to my motor
now these wires can be any color it
doesn't really matter a lot of places
show them is like black and red but
they're not black and red I actually
dislike that these are labeled black and
red and they're labeled black and red
because on the real car they're black and
red but motors don't have a black and a
red motors have an n + and an n -
because if you put power through one
direction it spins one way and if you
put power in the other direction it
spins the other way so really they
shouldn't be black and red they should
just be like white and blue or something
like that but you know that's fine
so to emphasize that I'm gonna make the
wires that go to them just be blue it
looks like my wire kind of goes under
the motor there and it looked like it was
disconnected so I'm gonna move it over
scooch so that is how we connect the
motor on the left side we're going
through things kind of fast but you can
always pause the video if you ever need
poor McKinley over here she's desperately
trying to keep up with me she's doing
good now we got to connect the
right-side motor and it's very similar it's
symmetric which is nice so I'm gonna
bring him down here and when it comes to
running wires you can see that I always
like to try to like run them a certain
way but there is no there is no wrong
way to run a wire right I'll have to
take a look at McKinley's board when
we're done here
I predict that she doesn't bother with
all the all the little movements that I
I tend to do right cool so I think that
that that's looking pretty good
all right now I was watching McKinley
over here and she was trying really hard
to figure out it's like does
this bottom wire go to the black and
then just the bottom wire over here go
to the red and she's like trying to make
sure that she gets it just perfect it
turns out that I don't care how I put
these wires in it's easier I guess if
you do it the exact same as me so we can
run into the same problems but what I'm
wiring a circuit like this I just plug
in the wires into the right spots and I
don't care if I get things crossed
because the worst thing that happens is
that my motor goes in reverse when I
start running and if it does I'll just
change the code to fix it right so
literally I decided where to connect
this wire honestly where ever it would
make my circuit prettiest but but if you
swap them and it doesn't really matter
because you can always fix it in code
later now the next thing we want to do
is we want to control the left motor and
control the right motor we want to
control the speed that it goes at and so
there's one pin that's like how fast
you go and so it's kind of like a knob
that you turn and then we want to
control the direction we either want to
go forwards backwards or reverse since
there's three options forwards backwards
I'm sorry forwards backwards or stop
since there's three options we actually
need two pins to do that so like it
could be like one zero because we're
one direction zero one it'll go the
opposite direction or zero zero it'll
stop so I need two pins to control the
direction and then the third one to
control how fast to do that so let's go
ahead and connect these three pins so
the first one I'm going to connect is
I'm going to connect the how fast pin so
I'm going to connect the top left which
is right there to pin 11 over here and
I'm gonna choose to make everything on
this side be green just so that I kind
of like don't get it confused and if you
want to to try to make it pretty
of course I want to try to make it
pretty you can add bins and things as
you see fit to try to pretty your
wires up some good enough I'll just leave it
right there so that one's going to pin
11 now I pick pin 11 let me put in a
little dip here just so you can see it
because it's got this little like tilde
in front of
a tilde in front of a pin means that it
can be used in analog output or PWM mode
so that way you can control it's not
just zero or one it can be anywhere in
between and so that's why that is on one
of those tilde lines now the other two
lines well there's only two lines left
on this side it's here and here they're gonna
go to 12 and 13 because they don't need
the ability to do an analog right and so
I'm just gonna go ahead and connect this
guy to 12 and then I'll connect this one
right here let's see if I can work my
way around this guy to 13 so I've got
three wires that control the left side
and one of them is special it's like the
the how fast and it's in the upper left
of the chip and it's going to pin 11
which has that little tilde symbol right
I'm gonna go ahead and connect my other
wires while I'm here just kind of while
I'm in wiring mode and the right side
the lower right controls his speed and
I'm gonna connect him to pin 3 and just
to kind of like make him all the same
maybe I'll use yellow wires for him
right now I chose to connect him to pin
3 because pin 3 also has one of those
little tilde jobbies so if you look
right there if your eyes are super good
it's got a tilde jobbie and then the other
two pins on the side I'm just gonna
collect nearby I see 2 & 4 are available
so I'm just gonna connect one of these
to 2 and then the other one to 4 so now
I've got my control line set up so the
the microcontrollers whole thing is he
controls what the H bridge does and then
the H bridge is in control of driving
the actual motors and you can look at
the data sheets for how these work and
why these pins are put in like this but
I think it's a pretty pretty good way to
arrange it there are different ways to
arrange an H bridge but I won't do that
as we're doing wiring let's go
ahead and wire up our potentiometers our
potentiometers on the top
top we're gonna put a connection to
power and on the bottom we're gonna put
a connection to ground and I'm gonna use
little power for this because I don't
want to like drive a motor or anything I
just want to be able to do control
things so I'm going to take the top to
power the bottom to ground on that one
and on this one and again you can see I
just connected the power to
somewhere in this row and then the
ground to somewhere in this row and then
here the top is to power the bottom is to
ground
alright so let's connect our last two
wires we want to connect the middle of
this potentiometer this is the analog
signal to a0 doesn't matter what
color wire you make it I feel like
purple just because purple is fun and then
I'm gonna connect the middle of this one
to a1 pretty impressive circuit that
we built here so we've got two
potentiometers which we're gonna use to
control the amount of the speed we've
got three control lines for the left
motor direction and how fast three
control lines for the right motor and
then we've got the motors connected down
here and then we've done some things to
like have big power and little power
right people also call it unregulated
power and regulated power so now we're
ready to see if we've done anything
useful at all by testing it in code so
the first thing I want to do to save it
is I want to call this my remote control
car when you change the name and you
type in your new name so your remote
control car it does automatically save
it I think you see up here it says all
changes saved all right so let's dive
into code now when it comes to the code
we've got a lot of things to test a lot of
things to test so let's go ahead and
we'll just kind of pick where we want to
start we're gonna do everything with
text today so go and switch it over to
text mode are you sure you want to
switch to text and be like yeah that'd
be fine and I don't want any of their
current code
so nothing that they put on here is
useful for us it was about flashing LEDs
we did LEDs and push buttons our first
day on Tuesday the second day by the way
we did analog so you should already know
about those and LCDs and servos and then
today we're doing motors I'll tell you
what since we already know about analogs
maybe we'll start with those so the
first thing I want to do is I want to
make some variables I'm going to make a
variable called left pot and right pot
they're going to both be integer
variables and what I'm going to do is
I'm going to read the left pot and right
pot and I'm going to print the values
just to make sure that the values kinda
look good so there's my two variables
left pot right pot normally with the pin
you have to do some setup for it which
would be in the setup area but there's
no setup for analog input that's
the default which is nice so I'm gonna
say my left pot and I'm just going to
type this fast you can pause it if you
need is an analog read and we got to
figure up where he's connected to so my
left pot right here if i trace the wire
he is on a1 so I want to do an analog
read of 1 you can also type a1
I can like just typing in the number 1 and
it works so I like to do that and then
we'll do an analog read for the right
pot this is my right side pot and he's
connected to a0 so I'm just going to
type in a 0 now just to make sure that
it's working I'm going to print the
value to the serial monitor so you can
see where it says serial monitor down
here so the serial monitor is
communication while the program is
running communication between your
computer and your Arduino board so it's
kind of interesting that your computer
is used to program it so like you send
the program over and then you're then
you're done with it but you can also
communicate with it while it's running
through the serial monitor and the
serial monitor is new today and we're going
to spend a lot of time right
so the first thing we have to do to use
the serial monitor is we have to type a
command called serial begin whenever you
do serial communication you have to
decide how fast it's going to go and so
your computer and your board have to be
speaking at the same speed to hear each
other if you just talking different
speeds it doesn't work this number right
here is 9,600 bits per second so they
talk fast right so they're talking like
they're saying like 10,000 things a
second if you talked and said 10,000
words a second it would go very badly and
what I want to do is I want to print out
those values so what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna print I'm just gonna make a little
message here I'm gonna say L is equal to
and I'm just gonna type the whole thing
here and you can type it up whatever
speed you type L is equal to left pot
and then I'm going to type R is equal to
a right pot I'm certain that you type at
a different speed than me but I have no
value in typing it slow so I just do it
fast and then you can catch up now what I
want to do is you'll notice that these
are all print statements so they stay on
the same line
I want the last one to go onto a new
line and to make something go onto a
new line you can put this ln on here
it's sends the newline character at the
end so that way all four of these things
the L the Left Pot reading the R the
right part reading are on one line then
it'll go to the next line now if I just
did that it would print out super fast
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna put a
delay in here of one second now this
code is really just test code it's to
see if our potentiometers are hooked up
correctly and if it works then my goal
is to delete it all when we're done
right but that's my goal so I'm going to
go ahead and run mine you'll have to
pause the video as necessary to get
yours to work but I'm gonna click on
start simulation and right now I'm
printing things to the serial monitor
so I've got to see the serial monitor so
I click on serial monitor and you can
see that it's printing out L 0 and R 0
all the way if I switch this guy to like
in the middle for the right one
you can see that it says 511 that's
right at the middle good job me and if I
click it like all the way up like near
the max it should be 1023 left should
also be movable so there it's 1023 and
then there it's 511 and then here it's
well it looks like it's about 164 again
it's important to note the range of
these things they go from 0 all the way
up to 1023 now it turns out for motors
motors you're gonna also run in the same
range from 0 to 1023 they run about as
fast as they're gonna run anything like
300 above they all run about the same
that's just a feature of motors and if
you want to run it lower you kind of
have to go somewhere in this range so
I'm gonna put mine like straight down
and so straight down is gonna run at
kind of like a middle speed right so
it's gonna run at kind of a middle speed
now it depends on the motor now the nice
thing is that we are using simulated
motors and they work perfectly but
that's going to be a good speed for a
lot of real motors by the way you'll
notice that the motors have a little
indication on them here they say zero
rpms that's zero revolutions per minute
alright so my analog inputs work I'm
quite confident that they work once I'm
confident that my code works I sometimes
just comment it out right so I know I
know it's frustrating it's like I just
typed all that code and now you're
telling me to comment it out very common
to test some small piece see that it
works but we don't need to be printing
all the time so I'm gonna take it out
and then to kind of move on to the next
piece all right so it's time to test
some more hardware it looks like the
next thing we need to do is we need to
start tackling our motors so we're going
to start by laying a little groundwork
for our
motors so functions are things that you
can call so for example here's a
function analog read one analog read
zero another function for delay what I
wish we had as I wish we had a function
where we could just say like left motor
and we could just give it a number we
just say like five hundred and I wish we
had a function that you said right motor
you go at negative five hundred and if
we had a function that we could just do
things like that then our motors would
be much more useful right because we
could just say go at this speed so like
five hundred would be like a middle
speed negative five hundred would be
like a middle speed but in reverse if I
wanted to stop it I could just say you
know stop zero right so I wish that
those functions exist all right I wish
that they did exist but they don't right
and so we have to write that function
and the reason they don't is obviously
people could write them but everybody's
different right so where you hook up
your wires and things so we're going to
make those functions so we haven't made
functions yet but they're extremely
powerful and we're gonna make these two
functions we're gonna do left together
and then we're going to have you try to
do the right one by yourself so I'm
gonna make a little space here so this
function for a left motor it's going to
take in one what's called an argument
for speed this argument that it takes in
so here we called it we said hey left
motor go at 500 this is what the syntax
looks like in C to make a function it's
kind of confusing by the way but it's
saying here that we're passing in 500
which is an integer and then whenever we
pass in that number it becomes the value
speed so don't type this but I'm just
gonna say so if i said Serial.println(speed)
it would print out 500 in
this case right because i passed it in speed
and if i put in you know like 50 then of
course this print would print out 50
because speed becomes 50
you get the idea alright that was
just an example so we want to do is we
want to drive the motors depending on
the value of speed now the first thing
we need to know is we need to know if
speed is positive or negative so if
speed is positive we'll do one thing and
if it's negative we'll do something
different and if it's zero we'll do
something even different so here's how
this works so if so we use a lot of if
statements in coding if speed is greater
than zero then run the lines of code
that I put in here before I put that
code in I'm gonna do some more things if
speed is less than zero I do this stuff
so the syntax is hard but the concepts
we want to care about you learning so
if it's greater than zero do this stuff
and then else meaning if it's not
greater than zero check to see if it's
less than zero
now there's one number that doesn't
satisfy either criteria so if it's
greater than zero do that if it's less
than zero do this
sissy have you figured out what the
other number is what's the other number
too busy trying she's panic trying to to
type the other number is zero itself
right so if it's bigger than zero do
this if it's less than zero do this and
if it is zero do this so those are
kind of the three situations and so that
is go forwards go backwards or stop
those are kind of our three options now
we've got to figure up how do we how do
we go forwards how do we go backwards
how do we stop and the way we do it is
we do digital writes to our different
control pins so I'm gonna say digital
right this is my left motor so these are
my green lines so the digital ones are it
looks like 12 and 13 so I'm gonna say 12
go
hi and 13 go low so what that will do is
those are my two control lines so
remember I said how if one of them's one
and then the other zero then it'll go in
that direction and then if you want to
go in the opposite direction I'm just
gonna copy those two lines and I'm gonna
switch it I'm gonna do a low and a high again
I'm typing ludicrously fast but that's
because with the beauty of videos you
can pause it right so so that's kind of
the idea so if it's going forwards do a
high and a low if it's going backwards
do the reverse a low and a high so you
do the exact opposite now if you're not
moving at all so if you're stopped so I'm
going to copy this down to the stopped
area we just bring them both low you could
also bring them both high that also
works if they're the same it stops it
the ones called coasts the other is
called break but it doesn't matter that
that will stop it now the thing
we've neglected here is how fast do you
want to do that right so we can do
better than just go we can actually like
set the speed to set the speed we have
to do an analog write the analog write
is a different command right and analog
writes are only possible on pins that
have this little tilde right so it
says somewhere on here at least on real
board it does yeah so PWM is a tilde
right and so analog write
if you send 500 that sends like roughly
two and a half volts and we can control
the speed so each time I want to control
the direction and I also want to control
the speed now in the second case since
speed is negative I have to put a
negative sign in front of here and the
reason for putting that negative sign in
front of there
it's because two negatives make a
positive right so if it was negative 500
that I do this to control the direction
but then the thing I actually analog
is always a positive number so
it's there and then our last case
doesn't matter what we put in for speed
it's actually ignored but I like to be
thorough so I'm just gonna put an
analogue write of zero now I've written
a bunch of code here and I have not
worried about direction at all and the
reason I haven't worried about direction
at all is because I can always change it
let's say that my wiring is such that
you know 12 and 13 high-low actually
make it go reverse I can always just
change it later I didn't worry about it
because I'm just gonna test it and see
what happens
and then I'll go from there all right so
I think I've got some code that's ready
to test before I test it I'm gonna
comment out this call to write motor
because we haven't written that function
yet if you try to call a function that
doesn't exist
bad things happen so the first thing I'm
going to do is I'm going to show you
what happens if you have made an error
so I'm just going to intentionally make
an error here maybe I put a bunch of
e's in speed that time the way you
check it for errors is you just click
run and if it has an error you see a
bunch of red nothing wrong with red red
is red is part of coding right so I'll
fix that one now let's see if I made any
accidental errors so I don't have any
accidental errors which is good so now
what I want to see is I want to see if
my motor is spinning her or not right and so
it looks like my motor is currently
humming along with the code that I put
in it's running at a hundred and
fifty-two rpms kind of fluctuates
between 152 153 they just kind
of put that in the simulation for fun
let's run it a little slower and see
what happens so let's stop the
simulation let's run it at 100 and hit
start simulation and whenever I run it
at 100 you can see that it's running
quite a bit slower now we went to all
the trouble to make this potentiometer
let's run the left motor at
left pot speed that'll be kind of fun so
now it'll run at whatever speed the
potentiometer is getting now this is
interesting it says zero why is it zero
actually that's like a real question
sissy why is it zero
I don't know why it's zero all right so
mine is really freaking out
and so the problem so I made a
mistake right just straight up I made
a mistake but I'm gonna just kind of
figure it out with you so when it's all
the way down at zero when I speed it up
a little bit it looks like it's going at
5 or 1000 sorry 100 and something then I
speed up a little bit more it's going
faster so that's good speed up a little
bit more and boom it just drops to like
6 or something I'm pretty sure we'll test
this that the problem is and I just made
this bug legit that's how programming
works I forgot to set any of these pins
as outputs right so I got lazy
so for digital sorry for analog inputs you
don't have to set up anything but for
other things you you gotta set up the
pins right and so I think that almost
certainly what's wrong is that I didn't
set up any of the pins to be outputs and
that's what's really causing this thing
to freak out so I've got 6 output pins
here I've got eleven twelve and thirteen
which are for one motor and then I've
got two three and four which are for the
other motor now I'm not using that other
motor yet but it really was
messing with me that it wasn't working
right I think it's just that they
weren't actually set as outputs alright
so let's try this out so I start slow
and then I move up and then it gets
faster it gets faster oh and then at some
point it goes slower again I actually I
made another bug it's all about bugs
today here's the bug
easy to fix the speed right here doesn't
actually go from zero to a thousand it
goes from 0 to 255
that was a goof on my part so I've got
to change something since I want to use
the pots here's what I'm going to change
inside of here I'm just going to do a
divide by four and that's because
analog write goes from 0 to 255 I forgot
thats Arduino worked not zero to a
1023 so I'm just gonna do a
divide by four right there and a
divide by four right there and life
will get quite a bit better all right
sorry
made multiple bugs there I could refilm
them obviously but I choose not to
because bugs are are part of how things
work right so now things should work
better so my left pot is down here it's
going like 24 and then as I speed up a
little bit more it goes like 70 70 or 80
as I speed up even more it goes at like a
hundred and thirty and then my max speed
is about 160 for this motor so now my
range is much better cool so that is
now some successful code woo was that
painful sissy hey
that's how it really goes but I did fix and
get the output set up and I did fix to
get the speed set up there all right now
what I want you to do is I want you to
set up the same thing on the right all
by yourself so I want a function called
right motor and right motor takes a
value that goes from zero to
1023 is technically the the range I
usually just do a zero to a thousand
because it's much cleaner and it's gonna
control the three pins on this side so
it's gonna control pin 4 pin 2 and
pin 3 and pin 3 as you can see it's
the analog one right so see if you can
follow the pattern of left motor and
make it for right motor and really the
thing that's going to change the big
thing that's going to change is the pin
so instead of being in 11 12 and 13
where
was the analog now you're going to be in
1 2 3 where 3 is the analog so see if
you can make that happen
all right so I wrote mine and the way I
did it is I cheated of course I copied
my other one and just anywhere where I
had an 11 which was the analog I switch
that to the 3 and anywhere there
was a 2 I made that our 12 I made that a
2 and anywhere it was the 13 I made it
a 4 now there is entirely a
possibility that my motor is gonna go
backwards as soon as I run this that's
ok I'm not I'm not too worried about it
I will just let it happen and then I'll
fix it if I need to fix it I'm gonna
choose to call right motor with the
right potentiometer and hit start
simulation cool and so now it should be
running it looks like it's doing pretty
good I'm gonna hide the code here just
so I can see it and so right now my left
motor is stopped again but that's just
because I left the potentiometer down
all the way so I could run them at max
speed so it's like 150 160 and run this
one at max speed and I've got a cool
little program here now what I'm gonna
choose to do is I've got the actual
hardware so I'm going to go ahead and
try this program on the actual hardware
and so what this is gonna do is this is
gonna make my car like drive around
which could be fun right so control a
control C I realize that it's unfair
that I have the hardware here and you
don't but I like to show you oops gotta
plug my hardware in I like to show you
what it is that you're making like on a
real car and so we'll go ahead and try
some things with the actual device all
right so I've got mine programmed on
here let's try it out so what it should
do as we put it on a table it should go
at a certain speed which is good and
then if I take these potentiometers and
I just crank them up
it should go faster which is fun and if I
take these potentiometers and I turn
them way
down then it's like barely going at all
and it's going so slow that it may not
even work when I put it on cool and so you can see there that
it's going super slow cool and so you can see that our code does work on a
real car which is fun and we've learned
how to wire motors alright so this last
part is optional if you want to call
this video done here you can I probably
would have taken this 1000 down to
something smaller but if you want to
call it done right now you can be done
but I'm going to show you some other
neat thing that we can do with serial
monitoring so serial monitoring you can
send messages to your car and you can
also print things from your car and what
you can do is you can actually instead
of just always going at these speeds you
can listen for the serial monitor so I'm
just gonna go ahead and type this and
then I'll talk about it so if there are
bytes available like from your computer
if you're if your computer sent some
bytes over then we can see what your
computer sent over and then we can
respond accordingly and so what we can
do is we can receive a byte so this is
the message from your computer we're
gonna say serial dot read and depending
on what your computer says so like
maybe your computer says forwords then
you can do things appropriate for
forwards so type that really fast you can
pause it and get caught up but if they
send a message for forwards then what
you might do is you might make the car
go at whatever your potentiometers say
to go ask right and you can do as many
different commands as you would like so
that one's forwards let's say that I
wanted stop right so if I say stop then
I can make them both go at zero and I
think that that's enough to try it right
so now I can turn my motors on to go at
the potentiometer speeds or stop
so if I hit start simulation what's
happening right now is nothing's going
yet but I can click on my serial monitor
and I can send these messages right so
I'm going to clear off my old messages
so I'm going to send a capital F and if
I hit Send then both of my motors start
going at wherever their pots are set and
if I send a capital S that makes them
stop and that's what we were kind of
showing with a real car at the beginning
now you could improve upon this a number
of different ways
again all optional but you can do as
many commands as you'd like you can also
to make your program easier to debug you
can respond backwards with things like
forwards so this is the Arduino
microcontroller responding back message
so if you do like a a forward so respond
back hey forwards and then it'll do it
if you send S it'll send back hey stop
and then it'll do it if you want to you
can make as many commands as you like
right so maybe I'll make a left
that'll say left and left will make the
the right pot go so you turn left by
making the right wheel go right and you
do the reverse for right you make the
left wheel go and then back it up which
normally I would call reverse but I've
already used R so back up and then there
you would go at negative of the left pot
and negative of the right pot by the
way on these turns if you'd like you
can also make it spin in place so you
can make like instead of the motor just
stop you could make it go negative which
would be in reverse again typing things
beyond at ludicrous speed there so there's
no way that you keep up in real-time but
you can see my code and if you'd like to
try it you can type it in and you can
see how it behaves I think it's good to
kind of get an
example of it but if you did want to
just watch it is kind of a mountain of
code I do want to try it to make sure
that it actually is working for me
though so I start the simulation I say
forwards it's got to be a capital F so
I'm going to say forwards with a
capital F that works fine I'm gonna say
stop that works fine I'm gonna say back
it up and back it up make them both do
it negative and negative if I do a left
spin then my left one goes backwards my
right one goes forwards if I do a right
it does the opposite and then if I do
you know a stop it'll stop it I could
show this on the car but I think we're
starting to get kind of long and it's
the same as that first demo now the
downside of this demo is that you will
have to if you use a real car keep your cable
plugged in and then it will make your
real car go alright so this one was this
one was all about motors we saw how to
wire the motors this is a little bit
longer sorry about that but sissy do you
think that some of these things were
cool were a little bit spoiled
because you got to play with an actual
car whereas other people only got to do
a simulation just a little cool so I
wanted to show you about motors motors
are an important thing to do if you kind of
get into the hobbyist world tomorrow
what we're going to play with is we're
actually done with circuits so this was
our whirlwind Tinkercad circuits
tomorrow we're going to do something new
in Tinkercad called code blocks and
it'll be kind of fun we look forward to
seeing you there bye
[Music]